大家好，我是 Olivia，目前在待業中，很開心能夠
Hi, I'm Olivia. I'm currently unemployed, and really happy to be able
跟我的好朋友 Nina 一起來做這個 podcast 的第一集，大家好
to do episode one of this podcast with my good friend Nina. Hi everyone,
我是 Nina，跟 Olivia 講的一樣，就是我們
I'm Nina — same as Olivia said, we
最近呢終於又在 reconnect，又聊，稍微聊了一下，想想啊
recently reconnected, talked a bit, thought about
目前的人生狀況啊跟未來的人生，然後彼此就分享到說
where our lives are right now and where they're going, and shared that
其實我們都在想要做 podcast，想很久了，但一直都沒有做起來，應該是一直都沒有踏出去
we'd both been wanting to do a podcast for a long time but never started — never took that first step
所以這次其實很興奮，就是有一個機會也可以跟 Olivia 一起搭檔
So this time it's exciting — a chance to team up with Olivia
然後開始我們這個的《The Long Way Here》的 podcast，那今天的第一集
and start this podcast, The Long Way Here. So for today's first episode
就是也想要趁機稍微聊一下啊最近發生的事情
we also wanted to take the chance to talk about what's been going on recently
一些職場上生活上面發生的事情
some things happening at work, in life
然後呃，最貼切的實事就是 lay off
and, well, the most relevant current event is — a layoff
（噹噹噹噹噹噹）哈哈哈，然後為什麼我們會有這件事情發生
(dun dun dun dun dun dun) hahaha. So why did this even come up
也是因為
it's because
本人呢很不幸的在之前被裁員了，領取大禮包
I unfortunately got laid off recently — got the severance package
然後那天跟 Nina 提起的時候想說，哎，能夠幹嘛呢
and that day when I brought it up with Nina, I said, hey, what can I even do
好像是不是可以搞一些事情，畢竟現在就是時間最多的時候
maybe I could do something, since I've got the most free time I've ever had
所以想說，哎，弄一下好了，嗯，所以我們就有了第一集的發想
so I thought, okay, let's just do it — and that's how episode one came about
對，所以第一集就是稍微講一下跟 layoff 相關的，其實我想到
Right, so episode one is basically about the layoff. Actually, that reminds me
我 3 年前其實自己也有被 layoff 過，哈哈哈，所以說學姐學姐好、學姐好
I got laid off myself three years ago too, hahaha, so — senior, hey senior
這也沒什麼好學不學姐的，就是純粹感覺就是人生應該都是
not that there's really anything to learn from being senior at this, it's just that life seems like
好像是一個必經之路
something everyone has to go through eventually
哎真的，人就是覺得
really, people just feel like
之前不是有個說法嗎，大家都說好像躲子彈，但是還是有些人躲不掉
there's that saying, right — everyone says it's like dodging a bullet, but some people don't dodge it
嗯，就像這次一樣
and, like this time
啊，還是沒有躲掉，也自我介紹一下
I didn't dodge it either. A bit of self-introduction:
2013 年來美國讀西北大學的 IMC program
I came to the US in 2013 for the IMC program at Northwestern
然後畢業之後就在美國成功找到工作
and after graduating found a job successfully in the US
2018 年後來有幸被 Nike 邀請到 Oregon 來
in 2018 I was lucky enough to be brought to Nike in Oregon
就一路到現在大概已經 7 年半
and that's been about 7.5 years now
8 月其實滿 8 年，所以是一個蠻長的過程
8 years this August, so it's been a pretty long stretch
嗯，就是從一個小小的 annual 職位，一路升到 director，然後
I went from a small annual-level role all the way up to director, and then
最後的一份子，其實說實在的，我覺得不太符合我的 background
the last part of it, honestly, I don't think really fit my background
因為變成一個 engineering manager，算是 BI
because I became an engineering manager, specifically BI
reporting engineering manager
所以那時候本身是可以把事情做完的
so at that point I could get things done
但就是覺得這不是我喜歡的東西，所以當 Nike 在 3 月
but I just felt like it wasn't what I loved. So when Nike, in March,
有提及要 lay off 的時候，我當下就有點感覺
mentioned they'd be doing layoffs, I felt something right away
然後覺得說，哎，可能也是個契機
and thought, hey, maybe this is actually an opportunity
是不是可以好好想一下下一步，所以那時候其實就開始
a chance to really think about what's next — so around then I actually started
開始在看看工作
quietly looking at jobs
然後是後來，後來就越來越覺得，啊也是吧，我就 8 年了，在這裡
And then, later, I started feeling more and more like — yeah, it's been 8 years, and here
的確是一個很好的學習環境，不過也覺得是時候該走了
really has been a great environment to learn in, but I also felt it was time to move on
就是有種停止學習自己想要學的東西的感覺，所以後來領到大禮包的時候
there was a sense of no longer learning what I actually wanted to learn. So when I got the severance package
就有一種感覺，是一種契機，但當下被裁——怎麼辦人生
there was this feeling, an opportunity, but in the moment, being let go — what do I even do
怎麼辦人生
with my life now
就有點迷茫，對，嗯，你們兩個當初是怎麼發生的
it felt disorienting. Right, so — how did it happen for you two?
妳可以講一下妳的經驗嗎？那我也分享一下我前面的經驗好了
Can you talk about your experience? Let me share my earlier experience too.
就先大方一點，我大概是 2010 年的時候來美國
Let me be a bit more open about it — I came to the US around 2010
那時候其實很幸運，因為疫情的關係，所以畢業就直接拿到綠卡
I was lucky, because of the pandemic, I got a green card right after graduating
拿綠卡來的，所以 2010 年來的時候，大概先在灣區這邊
with the green card already, so when I arrived in 2010, I was in the Bay Area first
先也很幸運找到一份工作，然後來到 2016 年的時候
and luckily found a job. Then in 2016
進去 Sifa 的美國總部，在裡面大概工作三年之後
I joined Sifa's US headquarters, worked there about three years, and then
2018 進到了美國 Copra 最後一間公司，叫做 Affirm
in 2018 landed at my last US company — Affirm
然後在裡面大概待了四年半，四年半的時間，其實見證了公司從 450 人
I was there about four and a half years, and in that time I watched the company grow from 450 people
一直到我離開的時候是 2,200 人，也是因為整個公司成長很快
to 2,200 by the time I left. Because the company grew so fast
所以到 2,200 人的時候就裁掉 500 人
once it hit 2,200 people, they laid off 500
所以我自己跟我下面的成員，其實
so between myself and the people who reported to me
聽說大概 90% 就被裁掉了，那其實在離開半年前
I heard about 90% got cut. Honestly, about six months before I left
大概就已經看到 writings on the wall
I'd already seen the writing on the wall
看到公司每 3 個月就做一次重組，每三個月就是嗯
the company kept restructuring every three months, every three months there'd be
換一些新的 project party，甚至那時候大概有兩個大頭，一樣的 C
some new project heads brought in — at one point two top executives, both C-level
就是 chief，一個是 COO 跟 CMO，都相繼離開
one was the COO, one the CMO, both left around the same time
那時候看到一些 CEO，跟看到我們那時候一些大頭離開，就覺得
seeing CEOs, seeing our own leadership leave, made me feel like
可能有一些變化要開始出現了
something was about to change
大概 2022 年年底就開始有一些裁員
layoffs started around the end of 2022
尤其是行銷部門被裁員，開始想說啊，呃，可能差不多了
especially in marketing, and I started thinking it was probably close
那我大概也開始想要去準備我的離開策略，所以那時候
so I began preparing my exit strategy. So around then
在被裁員的大概 4 個月之前，就開始準備了，準備包括就是去
about four months before I actually got laid off, I started preparing — including
想說自己下一步可以去哪裡，然後甚至開始受教練訓練
figuring out where I could go next, even starting coach training
但真的實際發生的時候，是 2023 年 2 月中的時候吧
But when it actually happened, mid-February 2023
實際發生的時候，其實也還是很 shock，尤其是那天我還進去公司
it was still a shock, especially because that day I'd gone into the office
要去工作跟兼職，然後順便去看一下醫生，然後那天
for work, planned to see a doctor on the side. And that day
呃，大概中午的時候吧，就先出去外面看醫生，走去的路上就發現
around noon, I stepped out to go to the doctor, and on the way I noticed
哎，就突然看到一個新的 meeting invite
a new meeting invite suddenly pop up
然後我們就馬上傳 Slack 跟我，那時候老板說
and I immediately got a Slack — my boss said
what's going on
然後但是後來邊走就想說，不對不對，這件事情要發生了
I kept walking but thought, no, no — this is about to happen
然後後來到了醫院之後就打了一針，打完針之後馬上在他那個後衛
After I got to the doctor's office and got a shot, right outside the building
就在那個醫院外面的後衛，就接了這通，大概有 10 分鐘的
outside the hospital, I took the call — about ten minutes
那時候是 CTO 跟 HRBP，就是
it was the CTO and the HRBP, which is
human resources business partner
直接在那個上面跟我講，但那時候其實是他的一個 presentation
who told me directly. But it was actually a presentation of his
是所有人都看得到，但每個人是一對一這樣子，每個人看不到其他人，哦是哦
that everyone could technically see, but delivered one-on-one, so no one could see anyone else
對啊，對哇
yeah, wow
我是 mass lay off，對，就是他直接裁了 500 人嗎
It was a mass layoff, yeah — he just went ahead and cut 500 people directly
對啊，所以那時候
yeah, so at that point
嗯，就還蠻 shock，但公司其實也蠻好的
it was still pretty shocking, but the company handled it decently
因為我還是回得了公司，他還是跟大家講說，呃，因為規模很大
because I could still go back into the building — he told everyone, because it was such a large scale,
所以他其實有給大家大概留一天的時間去收東西
he gave everyone about a day to pack up
那個時候公司其實是可以完全遠端的，但 hybrid 的話還是有辦公室
the company was technically fully remote-capable, but hybrid meant there was still an office
這時候其實還有辦公室，那天我回去之後就是也看得到整個公司還在裡面的人
The company still had an office at that point, and when I went back that day I could see everyone still in the building
就是大家都非常的慘澹，然後有跟我的組員講說，趕快開始收東西
everyone looking pretty grim. I told my team, start packing up right away
趕快把你的東西就是 archive 存起來，對啊，但是那天就是真的發生的很快
archive your files quickly. Yeah, but that day it really moved fast
但是對我來講，可能就是有一種啊 OK，要發生了，哦好，那就來吧的這種感覺
but for me there was this sense of, okay, it's happening, alright, let's go
那妳呢，感覺應該還蠻血淋淋的，剛剛發生，對，目前還有點
And you — that must still feel pretty raw, this just happened. Yeah, there's still a bit of
其實那時候第一個禮拜我還覺得我其實還好
Actually in the first week I felt like I was actually okay
因為就是有預兆嘛，就像妳說的，因為公司一直在重組
because there'd been warning signs, like you said, the company kept restructuring
Nike 的表現已經不太好了
Nike's performance wasn't great
重組裁員其實已經好幾次了，而且最大的一次，就是躲過那一次之後
there'd already been several rounds of restructuring layoffs, and the biggest one — after dodging that one
來到目前這一波，其實那時候就覺得公司不太穩
we got to this round, and by then I already felt the company wasn't stable
所以第一個禮拜接到消息的時候，我們公司走的流程是主管直接跟妳面談
So in the first week, when I got the news, our company's process was: your manager talks to you directly
然後跟 HR，所以他跟我講的時候的方式啊
then HR. The way he told me was
because the restructuring the roles
no longer needed
對，所以當下這個禮拜我覺得啊，whatever
Right, so that week I felt like, whatever
I knew it and Nike is not performing well, I understand
我覺得
I felt
當下能讓我感到欣慰的是，我的組員每個人都跑過來
what comforted me in the moment was every one of my team members came up to me
非常感謝我對大家的付出，然後最讓我感動的是，之前離開的 VP
thanking me for everything I'd done for them, and what moved me most was a VP who'd left earlier
跟所有的 leadership，他們都一個一個跑過來跟我說
and the whole leadership team, they came up to me one by one and said
stay connected，我記得非常清楚，然後
stay connected — I remember that so clearly. And
我當下其實非常驚訝，因為我跟那個 VP 並沒有
I was genuinely surprised in the moment, because I wasn't
到那麼熟，所以他知道我這個人的時候，我非常驚訝之外
actually that close with that VP, so I was surprised he even knew who I was
而且我想說是誰跟他說的，怎麼感覺那個 information 已經繞了一整圈
and I wondered who told him — it felt like the information had gone all the way around
當然後來他也說他一直都知道我是誰，所以當下心情有比較好一點
of course he later said he'd always known who I was, so that made me feel a bit better
然後最重要的是，呃，我之前 Nike
And most importantly, another
的另外一個 VP 也跟我說
VP from Nike also told me
Don't take it personally, it's not about you
當下真的有一種 self crisis，我其實現在都還有
in the moment it really did feel like a self crisis, and honestly I still carry
一定有啊，一定會，對對，所以我覺得說，未來
some of it now — for sure. So I want to say, in the future
有幸聽到我們 podcast 的人，如果妳也在經歷這件事情的時候
if anyone listening to our podcast is going through this too
就想跟妳說，feel all the feels
I want to tell you: feel all the feels
因為這其實算是一個 very unique experience
because this really is a very unique experience
對，就是讓那種痛苦難受的經驗
yeah, the kind of painful experience that made me
第一次在思考
think, for the first time
who define you, is the job define you, or you define yourself
who defines you — does the job define you, or do you define yourself
所以這件事情我到現在還在思考，要怎麼走過這件事情
so I'm still thinking through this one, still working out how to get past it
嗯，那妳們兩個當初有這種感覺嗎
Did you two feel this way at the time?
我覺得就像妳剛剛講的那些情緒，其實都有，可能都有
I think all the emotions you just described, they're all there, probably all of them
在當下，甚至結束之後的幾個禮拜都還有，甚至我覺得半年之後都還有
in the moment, even weeks after it ended, even I think six months later they're still there
就是偶爾想起來的時候，如果當下那天狀態不太好，或者今天天氣可能不太好
every so often, if you're not having a great day, or the weather's not great
可能就會突然讓自己的情緒開始陷入一些
it can suddenly drag your mood down into some
不管是自我懷疑，或是 self pity，或是會去懷疑
self-doubt, or self-pity, or start questioning
自己的價值到底在哪裡
where your own value actually comes from
但是我記得很清楚，我覺得那一天
But I remember very clearly, that day
或者說 the aftermath, maybe within seven days
or the aftermath, within about seven days
我覺得最大的情緒是 relief，就是一種啊嗯
I think the biggest emotion was relief. Like,
這樣了，我可以走了，我可以走了，那就走吧，讓我放下吧——這種 relief
okay, that's it, I can go now, I can go — so let's go, let me let it go, that kind of relief
或者說終於不用被工作困住，我終於可以稍微 relief
or, finally not being trapped by the job anymore, finally getting some relief
from all the stress in work
from all the stress at work
所以最大的應該還是一種坦然跟接受
so the biggest thing was probably a sense of calm acceptance
的這種感覺，嗯嗯，我也可以理解，因為那時候
Yeah, I get that, because in that first week
嗯，第一個禮拜的確是這樣想，就有一種放鬆感
I really did feel that way too, there was a sense of relief
這樣很鬆弛感，嗯，所以說第二個禮拜之後
kind of loose and relaxed. So then in the second week
面的感覺來的時候，就有點不太能夠調適了，嗯對，嗯對啊，我覺得
when the real feelings came, I couldn't quite adjust to it anymore. Yeah, and I could hear
我有聽到妳在說的過程，甚至是妳的口氣，其實也有一些
it — even in how you were talking, there was some
無奈，有一些 disappointment，然後有一些抱怨，對啊，做了這麼多努力
helplessness, some disappointment, and a bit of resentment — like, after putting in so much effort
之後，其實好像有一種
it feels like it was kind of
浪費的感覺，但是
a waste. But
另外一方面，其實也像妳剛剛講到的，好像有人幫我們做決定了，OK？
on the other hand, like you said, it's also kind of like someone made the decision for us, right?
對啊，因為可能想要離開，或是懷疑這份工作，或現在做的這件事情
Because whether you want to leave, or you're doubting whether this job or what you're doing
是不是自己想要做的，我相信自己在還在工作的時候也會有這些想法
is really what you want — I believe I had those thoughts even while I was still working
但真的要有這個驅動力讓自己決定要斬斷這個 connection
but actually having the drive to cut that connection yourself
是很難從自身生出來的，所以如果有一個人幫妳決定了，那種
is really hard to generate from within. So if someone makes that decision for you, that
破釜沉舟，要真的開始努力
burn-the-boats determination to actually start pushing
去下一個路線打拼的這種決心
toward the next path
我們可能也不會有這個機會，這個 party
we might never have gotten that opportunity, this whole thing
對沒錯，也是很有緣分，所以要感謝老天、感謝全公司幫我們累哦
Right, exactly, it's kind of fated too — so we should thank the universe, thank the whole company for wearing us out
這樣的意思嗎，哈哈哈哈，還沒有到感謝的地步吧，哈哈哈哈
is that what you mean? Hahaha. Not quite to the point of thanks yet, hahaha
呀對啊，所以我覺得這些情緒都是所謂的那個
Yeah, so I think these emotions are what's called
different stages of grieving
但它又會回來，又覺得 shock，然後又生氣，然後又難過
but it keeps coming back — you feel shock, then anger, then sadness again
所以不是不相信——沒有，是相信的
so it's not that you don't believe it — no, you do believe it
對對沒錯沒錯，有時候甚至還會看到某些東西
yeah exactly, sometimes you'll even see something
然後突然又會撞擊到自己
and it suddenly hits you again
比如說有時候不小心打開——因為我現在其實很多時候會上一些社群
like sometimes I'll accidentally open — because I'm often on a certain community platform
上面就是寫文章，但後來發現有時候一點連結進去，就會看到
where people post articles, and then I'll click a link and see
哦別人又怎麼樣了、別人又怎麼樣了，然後有時候就會覺得被刺了一下，哎被刺了一下
oh so-and-so did this, so-and-so did that, and sometimes it feels like a little sting, a sting
就覺得說，好像我如果繼續留下去的話，也可以坐到那個位置
it makes you feel like, if I'd stayed, I could be in that position too
看到別人說，就會有一種——我沒有，我覺得
seeing someone else's post gives you this feeling — not that I don't, I think
會激發一種稀缺的感覺
it triggers a kind of scarcity feeling
所以嗯，其實沒有很喜歡那種稀缺感
so honestly I don't really like that scarcity feeling
所以有密信道嗎？哈哈，啊比較像是 scarcity
is there a private channel for that? Hahaha, more like scarcity
就覺得說自己沒有、別人有，我沒有
feeling that you don't have something that someone else has
但我看到別人有、我沒有的時候，就會覺得，那我是不是也要一下？或者說，哎，我是不是不夠好？
but when I see someone else has it and I don't, I start thinking, should I be doing that too? Or, am I not good enough?
哎，我是不是不應該那時候放棄，不繼續追求
should I not have given up back then, should I have kept pursuing it
對，但是有這種情緒的話，其實我會
Yeah, but when I notice I'm having that feeling, I'll
注意到自己有這種情緒，然後花一點時間跟精力去做 reframe
notice it, and then take some time and energy to reframe it
去做轉念，那有的時候
to shift my thinking on it. And sometimes
會覺得花精力在這個轉念上，或者是
I feel like spending the energy to reframe it, or
去告訴自己，哎，其實可以幫對方開心，雖然我最
to tell myself, hey, I can actually be happy for them. Though I
到後來都可以去轉念到很正面的，然後去為對方開心
usually do get to a genuinely positive place eventually, being happy for the other person
也會感激自己擁有的，但是當初剛遇到自己
and grateful for what I have too. But early on, when I was
都還在花一些精力去轉念的時候，後來就乾脆——那我就不要看那個平台就好了，哈哈哈哈
still spending energy trying to reframe it every time, I eventually just thought — fine, I just won't look at that platform, hahaha
不要看到就不會有這種感覺，對啊，的確的確，那
if I don't see it, I won't feel that way. Yeah, exactly, exactly. So
妳可以講講當初為什麼決定要轉
can you talk about why you decided to pivot into
去做 coach 和 career coaching
being a coach, career coaching
嗯，有什麼契機嗎？然後妳到底花了多少時間？因為其實我現在還在迷茫當中
what was the trigger? And how much time did it actually take you? Because honestly I'm still in the fog on this one
嗯
hmm
像我剛剛有提到，我其實在被裁員前半年就開始準備，不管是心理準備
Like I mentioned, I actually started preparing about six months before I got laid off — both mentally
或是開始做一些調查跟反思
and by doing research and reflection
去想自己的強項在哪裡，或自己喜歡的東西在哪裡
thinking about where my strengths are, what I actually enjoy
然後開始去做一些研究跟一些 MVP，去
and then starting to do research and some MVPs to
測試哪幾個方向是可行的，因為我其實一直以來都蠻喜歡做自我成長
test which directions were viable. I've always been into personal growth
跟心理學的內容，很關鍵的應該是——以前就知道日本的 Ikigai 這個概念
and psychology content, and one key thing was — I already knew the Japanese concept of Ikigai
就是四個項目：你在行的、你熱愛的
which is four circles: what you're good at, what you love
世界需要的，跟你可以得到回饋的，所以這是一個
what the world needs, and what you can get paid for. That was a
框架，是之前有學到的，後來 2021、2022 年的時候
framework I'd learned before. Then around 2021, 2022
看了一本書叫做《Designing Your Life》
I read a book called Designing Your Life
是史丹佛好幾個教授寫的
written by several Stanford professors
專門用 design thinking 的方式，去幫人們用一個框架
which specifically uses design thinking to help people use a framework
找出什麼樣的人生方向適合自己，那時候
to figure out what life direction actually fits them. Around then
2022 年也開始看這些書
in 2022 I started reading these books
做了很多自己的 reflection，也是在那兩個練習中
did a lot of my own reflection, and through those two exercises
慢慢找出一些新的方向——包括那時候開了一間跟環保
gradually found some new directions — including at one point starting a company related to
相關的公司；第二個可能是往所謂的 mental health 方向走
environmental sustainability; a second direction was maybe toward mental health
因為我覺得 mental health 對我來說
because I feel mental health is
是一件非常非常重要的事情
a really, really important thing to me
然後我也認為 mental health
and I also believe mental health
可以間接幫助地球，因為如果大家更能被 heal、被安撫的話
can indirectly help the planet, because if people can be more healed, more soothed
可能就不會做這麼多的消費行為
they might not engage in as much consumption
因為很多時候消費行為只是一種滿足自己
because a lot of the time consumption is just a way of meeting
需求的方式吧，嗯，所以我那時候也認為 mental health 其實也是一個幫助地球
some other need. So at the time I also thought mental health was an industry that both helps the planet
又幫助人的產業，現在還有想到，那不然可以回去做瑜伽老師
and helps people. I even thought about going back to being a yoga teacher
或是去做調酒師，然後第五個就是去做社群
or being a bartender, and the fifth idea was building a community
所以那時候大家就是用這兩個框架，梳理出自己大概有哪些方向可以走
So at the time I used those two frameworks to map out roughly which directions were possible
然後這幾個方向之後就會去研究、調查，或問過曾經做過的人
and then for each direction I'd go research it, or talk to people who'd already done it
看這個方向是不是可行的
to see if that direction was actually viable
嗯，所以大概是用這樣的方式，去規劃出哪些可能性
That's roughly how I mapped out the possibilities
算是自己的 MVP 吧
call it my own MVP process
OK，對啊，我覺得我應該好好做一下，哈哈哈，我已經有 problem 了
Okay, yeah, I think I should really sit down and do this properly, hahaha, I already have a problem here
我還做了一個 e-book，可以再傳給妳，哈哈哈，好，沒問題，哈哈哈，那我待會傳
I actually made an e-book too, I can send it to you, hahaha. Okay, no problem, hahaha, I'll send
那個連結給妳，如果有人需要的話也可以，對對對對對
you the link in a bit — if anyone needs it, it's available too. Yes yes yes yes
哎，我覺得這是非常好的工具，說起來我之前第一個反應就是——那就去找工作吧
I think that's a really great tool. Honestly my first instinct back then was just — okay, go find a job
嗯，所以
so
3 月正式開始慢慢找工作的時候
when I actually started job-hunting seriously in March
其實就是很簡單地打開履歷網站
it was really just — open the resume site
改履歷、投履歷這樣子，嗯，所以並沒有很
edit the resume, apply — I hadn't really
認真地去思考除了工作之外還可以做什麼
seriously thought about what else I could do besides get another job
嗯對啊，所以當下我有一段
Yeah, so at that point I had a bit of
跟 Nina 那個經驗不太一樣——我在被通知之後的那個禮拜
an experience a bit different from Nina's — in the week after I got the news
我其實並沒有改變我的作息、生活或習慣
I actually didn't change my routine, my life, or my habits at all
就是一樣起床顧小孩，送小孩上課，然後開會
same thing: wake up, take care of my kid, drop the kid off, then meetings
然後投工作，那時候其實有好幾個面試，就是在準備面試這樣子
then apply to jobs. I had several interviews around then, so I was prepping for those
然後一直到 6 月初，可能我就是心態跟
Then going into early June, I think my mindset and
精神上就有點 burned out 了，直到我老公把我拉著坐
energy started getting a bit burned out, until my husband pulled me down to sit
下來，很認真地看著我的眼睛跟我說：You need to calm down
looked me right in the eyes, and said: You need to calm down
take a break，對，因為他
take a break. Yeah, because he
發現我情緒不太好，看到我 losing myself，所以那時候有人
noticed my mood wasn't great, saw me losing myself. So someone was
跟我說，應該要認真思考到底自己要幹嘛，畢竟大禮包真的有 cover 到一段時間
telling me I should seriously think about what I actually wanted, since the severance really did cover me for a while
國際學生也知道，妳拿 H-1B 的時候，如果要換工作
And as an international worker, you know — when you're on an H-1B, if you want to switch jobs
是必須馬上，嗯，隔天就要繼續有工作的
you basically have to have the next job lined up immediately, no gap
所以我就是這樣馬不停蹄地一直工作到現在
So I've just been working nonstop up until now
以我從 Discover 到 Nike 的整個經歷，是沒有一天沒有工作的
honestly, from Discover to Nike, there hasn't been a single day I wasn't employed
所以在那個轉職過程中，我並沒有休息過
so through this whole career transition I never actually rested
就是一路工作到現在，對，哈哈哈
just kept working straight through, hahaha
對，所以啊，我常常會跟我老公說，我好累啊
So I often tell my husband, I'm so tired
如果可以的話，我能不能休息一段時間？但是當下我個人可能是無限堅強吧
could I maybe take some time off if I could? But in the moment I guess I'm just infinitely stubborn about it
活在這麼多年的社會框架下
living for so many years inside a social framework
一直覺得說被認為有成就，就是要有工作、有好的
that says being seen as accomplished means having a job, a good
title、好的 social economic status，whatever that is
title, a good so-called socioeconomic status, whatever that is
就覺得這件事情才是對的，所以我覺得目前
it just feels like that's the correct thing. So I think right now
最大的一個體會就是，到底我想要什麼，我覺得
the biggest realization for me is — what do I actually want, I
我可能要好好去思考一下，因為真的有點忘記
probably need to sit down and really think about that, because I've honestly kind of forgotten
到底自己想要什麼
what I actually want
跟當初來美國的初衷、工作的初衷是什麼
what my original intention was coming to the US, what my original intention with work was
讓我最開心的事情是什麼？妳覺得妳有忘記嗎？因為聽起來妳剛剛講到
what actually makes me happiest. Do you think you've actually forgotten? Because from what you just said
其實也是因為習慣了要一直努力工作，然後因為有一份好工作
it sounds like it's also just become a habit — always pushing to work hard, and because you have a good job
一個好 title、一個好的所謂 social economic status
a good title, a good so-called socioeconomic status
這些其實就是妳一直記得、覺得很重要的東西
those are the things you've always remembered as important
應該這樣講
I guess I'd put it this way
它對我很重要，是一件事情
it's important to me
是因為我個人很在乎別人怎麼看我
because I personally care a lot about how others see me
所以那個價值是我給予他人的
so that value is something I'm giving to other people
嗯，當然也是我給予自己的自我成就感吧
and of course also giving myself a sense of accomplishment
但如果妳真的問我我想要幹嘛，我就會覺得，我好像並沒有為我自己
but if you really ask me what I want, I feel like I haven't really lived
活出我想要的那種感覺，我覺得我會有這種想法
the life I wanted for myself. I started thinking this way
是因為有一天我看了一個 reel，講的是兩個 traveler 遇到彼此
because one day I watched a reel about two travelers meeting each other
然後其中一個人就說：不要提及妳的 background 或妳的
and one of them says: don't mention your background or your
work，介紹妳自己
job, introduce yourself
tell me how much I can learn from you
我當下就想套在自己身上，結果我當下是一片空白，沒辦法有架
I tried applying that to myself in the moment, and I just went completely blank, couldn't give a
構性地介紹自己，講出一件除了工作之外可以拿出來讓我很驕傲的事情
structured introduction of myself, couldn't come up with one thing outside of work that I was proud of
哈哈哈，那時候還蠻沮喪的
hahaha, that was pretty depressing at the time
直到現在我還是在思考這件事情，然後現在剛好又遇到裁員
and I'm honestly still thinking about it now, and now on top of it I've just been laid off
嗯，所以把 title 跟 word
So once you strip away the title and the
拿掉之後呢，我現在就是回到我最初的那個問題
words, I'm right back to that original question
其實我之前也一直在用 AI 自我對談
Actually I've been talking to AI a lot to work through this myself
除了我的心理醫生之外，我還會跟 AI 聊，它也跟我提到
besides my therapist, I also talk to AI about it, and it told me
可能就像妳說的，我可能要 work on myself
kind of like what you said, that I probably need to work on myself
就是怎麼去接受自己，哈哈哈，嗯嗯，back to square one
which is how to accept myself, hahaha, back to square one
但是如果大家有興趣的話，我們下一集可以討論一下，哈哈哈哈
But if people are interested, we could do a whole episode next time, hahaha
自我的心路歷程啊，哈哈哈，自我心路歷程跟認同工作帶給自己的認同
on the inner journey of self-acceptance, hahaha, and how identity gets tied up with work
冒牌者症候群，其實很多東西可以聊
impostor syndrome — there's a lot to talk about there
對對，尤其是啊亞洲女性可以這樣講，嗯，那我不想要 generalization，不過我
Right, right, especially for Asian women — I don't want to generalize, but I
其實很常看到女性，或是亞洲女性
do often see that women, or Asian women
或是來國外工作的台灣人，嗯
or Taiwanese people working abroad
通常都會有一個習性，就是我們比較不懂得去 sell ourselves
tend to share this trait — we're just not that good at selling ourselves
我剛到 Nike 工作的時候，這是一個非常非常大的 culture shock
When I first started at Nike, that was a huge culture shock
因為在 Nike 的 workplace，大家都非常 outspoken
because in the Nike workplace, everyone is very outspoken
非常知道怎麼表達自己，讓別人看到你，對
very good at expressing themselves, making sure people see them, right
然後我還記得我當初的第一個主管也說，妳其實不用做太多
I still remember my first manager there telling me, you don't actually need to do that much
妳要有一個 signature project
you need one signature project
然後持續去 selling your signature project
and then keep selling that signature project
to let people know 妳到底會什麼，這是非常重要的
to let people know what you're actually capable of, that's really important
所以我覺得在過去 7 年半在 Nike
So I'd say what I learned over those 7.5 years at Nike
學到的就是怎麼去 sell myself，我覺得我們可以用另外一個時間
was really how to sell myself. We could set aside another time
跟大家討論一下，當妳有這個習性
to talk more about this — when you have this tendency
要怎麼先去 energize，然後怎麼走出 impostor
how do you first energize yourself, and how do you work your way out of impostor
syndrome 的那個過程，我們可以再看
syndrome — we could cover
一下，這個可以講很多，對啊，我扣掉也看到很多，我自己的積壓過程其實也有一些
a lot there. Yeah, I've seen a lot of this myself too, I have some of my own
自我的心路歷程可以分享，對啊，但我們可以另外錄一集
inner journey around this I could share. Yeah, but let's save that for another episode
那妳——妳花了大概多少時間，然後 build 一個 brand
So — how much time did it actually take you, to build a brand
因為妳剛才說妳已經花了大概
because you said you'd already spent about
三四個月去做一些 pre-work，然後後來才 launch，對
three or four months on pre-work, before you actually launched, right
大概花三四個月 pre-work，然後大概有半年的時間去受訓，實際受訓做教練
About three to four months on pre-work, and then about six months of actually going through coach training
然後那半年——包括那時候也剛好碰到裁員——所以這半年就是有
And during that six months — which happened to overlap with the layoff — that's when I did
受訓、考證照，然後開始實際立案去開公司
the training, got certified, and then actually filed to start the company
所以那個就是在大概是 2023 年中，6 月的時候，就是現在
So that was around mid-2023, June, and actually — right now
其實剛過了公司的三週年慶
we just passed the company's three-year anniversary
啊
aw
哈哈哈，謝謝謝謝，對啊，所以大概花的時間是這樣子
hahaha, thank you, thank you. Yeah, so that's roughly the timeline
但我覺得在自己做 solopreneur 的過程中，其實會一直有很多的
But I think in the process of being a solopreneur, you're constantly getting a lot of
時間跟機會做 reflection，甚至做調整，像我雖然是做 coaching
time and opportunities to reflect, and even to adjust — even though what I do is coaching
但這個過程中其實也有一些機會，包括之前碰到的人脈
along the way there have been opportunities, including connections I'd made before
coaching 過程中碰到的人脈或機會，其實也做了很多新的事情，包括比較分析的顧問
people and opportunities that came through coaching itself, and I ended up doing a lot of new things — comparative analysis consulting
然後也有做 sponsor post，也辦了非常多活動
sponsored posts, and I've run a lot of events
線上線下都有，所以其實在這過程中一直會有一些小調整
both online and in person. So throughout this whole process there have always been small adjustments
不管是說 pivot on the content topic
whether that's pivoting on the content topic
我在講的是 pivot on
what I mean is pivoting on
嗯，什麼樣的 coaching client，就是什麼樣的人是我更想要服務的
what kind of coaching client, like which kind of person I actually want to serve
或是幫助的，其實一直都在小小地調整，但我覺得很關鍵的幾件事情：第一個
or help — it's always been small ongoing adjustments. But I think a few things are really key: first
要先停下來，給自己一些時間做反思跟復盤
you have to actually stop and give yourself time to reflect and review
然後去看看，OK，之前做了哪些東西做得好、做得不好
look back and go, okay, what did I do well, what didn't work
或哪些東西給自己帶來很多成就感、覺得很開心的
or what gave me a lot of fulfillment, made me happy
做得很投入、很有精力、很充電的
made me feel really engaged, energized, recharged
然後再從那邊去挖掘，或找出一些蛛絲馬跡
and then dig from there, look for clues
是不是有什麼新的東西可以去玩、去展開
about whether there's something new worth exploring, worth expanding on
所以其實是先給自己時間復盤，然後第二個就是說
So first, give yourself time to review. Second
復盤之後，用自己的規劃能力，再策劃出接下來
after that review, use your own planning ability to map out what to do next
如果要往這邊測試的話，不管是 MVP，或是真的有這個新的 project
whether that's an MVP or an actual new project
可以怎麼做
how to actually go about it
對，但我覺得允許自己有時間停下來去思考、復盤
Right, but I think allowing myself the time to stop, to think, to review
甚至休息，對我來說都很關鍵，當我聽到妳提到，妳覺得妳應
even to rest — that's been really key for me. When I heard you say you feel like you
該要想想自己要
should be thinking about what you want
是什麼讓妳覺得妳自己「應該要」
what's making you feel like you "should"
是因為發現身邊的人，或自己發現自己好像太累了嗎？就連工作都累了
I think it's from noticing, in myself or around me, that I'm just — tired? Even work has become tiring
然後現在連想要做下一步都累了，應該說
and now even thinking about the next step feels tiring. I guess it's
因為現在有小孩了，就非常務實
because I have a kid now, it becomes very practical
用比較現實的角度來看這件事情的話
a much more realistic lens on this whole thing
雖然目前的存款跟大禮包其實都可以維持一段時間
Even though my current savings and the severance can technically cover us for a while
但以現實的角度來看，就必須找收入去支持這個家
from a practical standpoint I still need to find income to support the family
我覺得，我覺得絕大部分是這個原因
I think that's most of the reason
然後第二個原因是，我真的認真覺得
The second reason is, I honestly, genuinely feel like
我還沒有給自己時間去思考
I haven't given myself the time to think
如果一定要有收入的話
whether, assuming I do need income
是不是有其他收入來源可以嘗試
there are other income sources worth trying
嗯，然後我覺得我現在就是，這是我目前的課題
I think that's the real question I'm sitting with right now
就是去了解到底有什麼方式可以達到
figuring out what ways there actually are to reach
然後並不一定要靠一份正職工作才行
financial income without it necessarily having to come from a full-time job
財務的收入，嗯，我覺得就是我目前在思考的
that's what I'm working through right now
嗯對，所以我覺得應該
Yeah, so I think
我們剛才說，應該其實一部分是來自於小孩的壓力
like we just said, part of it comes from the pressure of having a kid
當然不是說我們必須
not that it has to be this way
嗯，但就是 double income is better than one income
but, well, double income is better than one income
嗯，OK，那來談談有小孩跟沒小孩另外一種搭配
okay, so let's talk about the with-kid vs. without-kid version of this
對，我個人是還不想要放棄
Right, personally I'm not ready to give that up yet
我之前為自己的規劃就是希望在 50 歲之前可以退休，當然越早越好
my own plan for myself was to be able to retire before 50, and earlier if possible
然後我們之前在有小孩之前的規劃，是大概 45、40、50 就可以退休
Before we had our son, our plan was something like retiring around 45, or 40 to 50
但因為有小孩，就要推遲一點，所以如果我不想推遲，就必須繼續工作
but now that we have a kid, that gets pushed back a bit — so if I don't want to push it back, I have to keep working
對，第二個就是——我現在的思考方向
Right, and the second thing is — the direction I'm thinking in now is
帶給所有人一個很大的優勢，就是很多妳不太懂的事情
AI gives everyone a huge advantage — for a lot of things you don't really understand
妳可以透過 AI 去不斷提問
you can just keep asking AI questions
找方法，或找出路，然後妳可以慢慢知道自己要做什麼、可以做什麼
find methods, find a way through, and gradually figure out what you want to do, what you can do
或是有什麼其他方法可以做這件事情
or what other ways there might be to do it
我覺得這一部分，對我目前非常混亂的思考過程來說
I think that piece has given me, in the middle of what's otherwise a pretty chaotic thinking process right now
給了我一個很好的框架，所以我覺得接下來可能也可以開另外一個
a really solid framework. So I think going forward I might open up something else
好比跟大家分享——因為我目前有一個非常非常想做的概念
to share with everyone — because right now there's something I really, really want to do
是想用 AI 去做一些 passive income
which is using AI to build some passive income
嗯，然後當然就是目前很多的 Instagrammer
Of course a lot of Instagrammers
或 TikToker 都有在講這件事，但很少看到有人真正
or TikTokers are already talking about this, but you rarely see anyone actually
把每一個 passive income 來源講清楚——大家有時候會說，哇，多好多好
break down each passive income source in real detail — people will say, oh, so great, so great
faceless YouTube 會帶給妳多少什麼東西
look how much faceless YouTube can bring you
但很少人講到底要花多少時間跟精力才能做到這件事情
but very few people talk about how much time and effort it actually takes to get there
所以我想從我這次的契機出發
So I want to use this whole situation as a starting point
真正讓大家知道——如果妳要做這件事情
to actually show people — if you want to do this
你需要做什麼；如果要做到真的最後可以有收入的話
what do you actually need to do; if you want to get to the point where it's really generating income
你要花大概多少時間，付出多少心力
how much time do you need to put in, how much effort does it actually take
我覺得那個我目前很想做，然後嗯嗯，我已經有幾個 experiment 開始了
I think that's something I really want to do right now, and I already have a few experiments running
所以我現在就是已經有一個大概框架，所以想說這個是還蠻喜歡
so I've got a rough framework going already, and I'm really into it
嗯，可能也剛好我夠宅啊，哈哈哈，夠宅的情況下，而且我又很喜歡
maybe it's partly because I'm just a big enough homebody, hahaha, and I really like
那種 tech 跟數據的東西，所以嗯嗯
that tech and data kind of stuff. So
就想要把我目前學到的所有 AI，跟 onboard 到 AI 的那個過程
I want to share everything I've learned about AI, and the whole process of getting up to speed on it
跟大家分享，哇好多東西，所以聽起來其實妳已經驗證了這些
with everyone. Wow, that's a lot. So it sounds like you've already validated these
MVP 之後，然後現在其實已經更清楚一個點子是說
MVPs, and now you've got a clearer idea that
可以把妳做過的這些 experimentation 包裝成一個東西，然後分享
you could package up all this experimentation into something and share it
或者開始 monetize，是已經驗證到這個階段了嗎
or start monetizing it — have you validated it to that stage yet
後面還沒有，就是啊
not the back end yet, it's more
中間吧，就從做過 marketing strategy 的方式來看呢
in the middle, I'd say. From what I know of marketing strategy
就是要流量，然後妳就是要非常非常專注在
it's about traffic — you have to be really, really focused on
the platform having the consistent content
full steam every day to drive the traffic
然後它才會慢慢做起來，嗯，所以我覺得
and only then does it slowly start to work. So I think
一部分是我看到所有的 influencer 或
partly from watching every influencer or
任何 content creator，我覺得最重要最重要
any content creator out there, the single most important thing
最重要的第一個想法就是：不要為了錢而去做 content
first and foremost, is: don't build content for the money
嗯，去為了一個 passion 做 content 會比較能夠做得長久，嗯，因為
build content out of genuine passion, and it'll last a lot longer, because
除非妳運氣好到做出一個
unless you get lucky enough to land one
viral video、one-hit content，嗯，一夜成名
viral video, one hit piece of content, overnight fame
但是我覺得那個就像中樂透，那種機率不是不可能
but I think that's basically like winning the lottery, not impossible
但是機率就比較小，嗯，妳要很持續跟很穩定地走
but the odds are pretty low. You have to walk it consistently and steadily
慢慢做起來，才可以真正的，對
build it up slowly, to actually get there, right
走到最後那個階段，嗯
to that final stage
然後我覺得，可能有那麼一段時間，妳要有
And I think there's probably a stretch where you need
那種勇氣去做那段過渡期——就是至少半年到一年
the courage to get through that transition period — at least six months to a year
妳可能完全沒收入，然後直到慢慢有人發現妳
you might have zero income, until people gradually start discovering you
所以這也是我那時候在思考的：我到底可以真的用 passive income
So that's also what I was thinking about — can I actually use passive income
去取代我的 corporate job
to replace my corporate job
還是我還是可以繼續慢慢找工作
or should I keep slowly job-searching
嗯嗯，找到我自己最喜歡的，然後再做副業，反正我現在有很多時間
find something I actually love, and build the side project alongside it — since I have a lot of time right now anyway
我就用這段時間去 set up，所以之後有工作的話
I might as well use this time to set it up, so that once I do have a job again
再做起來就比較簡單，嗯對，了解，對，所以現在聽起來策略是，並沒有二選一
it'll be easier to keep it going. Right, I get it, so it sounds like the strategy isn't really either/or
就是兩個一起做
it's doing both at once
我覺得最實際，以我的個性跟所有的
I think realistically, given my personality and looking at all
數據來看，我覺得是先變成斜槓，然後再慢慢存這些
the data, I think it's — go slash-career first, and slowly build savings from that
看哪個好，再慢慢投入過去，對，但是我
see what works, and slowly put more into it. But my
對自己之後的一個期許是
hope for myself going forward is
我希望我不用再靠著 corporate 的方式去做
that I won't have to keep doing things the corporate way
因為到最後沒有了工作，到底有什麼是可以讓妳值得驕傲的
because at the end of the day, once the job's gone, what's actually left that you can be proud of
嗯，我覺得像 Nina，妳有自己的公司
I think with you, Nina, you have your own company
一個品牌 Wayfinder，也是一個 coach，我覺得那是一件很
a brand — Wayfinder — you're a coach, and I think that's something really
值得說出來的事——妳是為了自己去創造一個品牌
worth being able to say out loud — you built a brand for yourself
然後我也覺得我想要有一個
And I feel like I want that too — something that
something belongs to me, I'm the boss lady
belongs to me, I'm the boss lady
嗯對啊，那這樣真的聽起來，妳這 3 個月的確啊
Yeah, it really does sound like, over these three months
連這些反思題都很清楚了，就是妳現在很清楚地
even these reflective questions have become clear to you — you can now clearly
告訴自己、知道自己的期許——不管是遠期的
tell yourself, and you know your own hopes — whether that's the long-term one
希望自己在 50 歲可以退休，還是中期的，希望自己繼續有一份正職工作
wanting to retire by 50, or the medium-term one, wanting to keep a full-time job
同時開始去實現所願，這是妳自己在了解自己的過程
while starting to work toward what you actually want. This came out of your own process of understanding yourself
了解自己的過程中知道說這是最實際的一個方式，所以然後妳也知道現在
knowing that this is the most realistic path for you. So now you also know
其實現在有哪些 project 是自己在嘗試、想要開始
which projects you're already trying out, already wanting to start
去把它建立起來的，這些 side project，所以其實
building up — these side projects. So
很清楚啊，聽起來妳很清楚妳未來要做什麼跟現在在做什麼了
it sounds like you're clear on what you want to do in the future, and what you're doing right now
對吧？應該吧
right? I guess so
妳有沒有興趣把「應該」換成
any interest in swapping "I guess" for
或者是「對」
or "right"
哈哈哈，我再講一次，我再講一次——聽起來妳很清楚妳這要做什麼
hahaha, let me say it again, let me say it again — it sounds like you're clear on what you want to do
對吧
right?
對，哈哈哈
right, hahaha
連這個都要猶豫，沒關係沒關係，可以理解，我覺得
even hesitating on that. It's fine, it's fine, I get it. I found
我這過程中發現很多另外的話題，然後這也是第一集
a lot of other topics along the way here, and this is also episode one
所以也請大家多多包涵，如果你有想要問我們的問題，或想了解比較細節的部分
so please bear with us. If you have questions for us, or want more detail on anything
像是 coach 怎麼 set up，可以留言給我們，我個人會盡量分享剛才說的一些 like coach
like how to set up as a coach, feel free to leave us a comment, I'll do my best to share what I mentioned
然後一些就是怎麼 set up
and some of how to set it up
LLC，或是怎麼變成 LLC，那個證書要去哪裡考
LLC, or how to form an LLC, where to get certified
或怎麼準備，我們都可以做，然後我個人呢
how to prepare — we can do that. And on my end
就是剛才提到的 AI 搭建跟一些 side project，我覺得我
with the AI-building stuff and the side projects I mentioned earlier, I
也可能會用 update 的方式跟大家說我目前做到哪裡
might do updates letting you know where I've gotten to
然後哪些東西是我怎麼用的，也可以跟大家分享，嗯對，我覺得這些東西
and what I've figured out how to use, and share that too. Yeah, I think we
我們都可以繼續做下去，然後最後也要說謝謝 Nina
can keep building on all of this going forward. And lastly, thank you, Nina
今天跟我一起聊聊最近的 layoff，然後也聊到了
for talking through this recent layoff with me today, and for getting into
一些彼此人生的卡點跟彼此怎麼走過去，甚至是現在還在卡的這個過程中
some of our respective stuck points in life, and how we've each moved through them — or are still stuck in that process
然後也想要送給正在聽的大家：我們都很好，要相信自己很好，覺得我們都有
And I also want to send this out to everyone listening: we're all doing okay, believe that you're okay too, we all have
別人沒有的東西，對我們都可以的，我們我們可以
something that other people don't, we can all do this — we can do this
雖然有點 the long way here
even though it's kind of a long way here
但是 we will get there, we will get there
we will get there, we will get there
哈哈哈
hahaha
好了，今天就謝謝大家收聽《The Long Way Here》，yeah
Okay, thanks everyone for listening to The Long Way Here, yeah
請多包涵，第一集，不用包涵，OK，謝謝大家
please bear with us, this is episode one. No need to bear with anything, okay, thank you everyone
謝謝大家，哈哈哈，OK
thank you, hahaha, okay
拜拜。
bye bye.